"Pesticides (DDT) and
Alzheimer’s Disease"
Although there is a growing list
of Alzheimer's disease
susceptibility genes, even if
you put them all altogether,
they account for less than half
of all Alzheimer's cases.
The single most compelling piece
of data on the potential control
we have over the disease
is the fact that if you have
identical twins, with the exact
same genes, even if one gets
Alzheimer's the other
usually does not.
So, we have to think
about all the other
contributing factors
beyond just genetics.
In my video on pesticides and cancer,
I talked about this study.
There’s a list of chlorinated
pesticides, including DDE
(a metabolite of DDT) that
are classified by the EPA
as probable human carcinogens.
But in the study, blood
levels of DDE and others were
associated not with
increased cancer mortality,
but increased risk of
other-cause mortality.
This led researchers to
speculate it may be due to
an associated increased risk
of diabetes or dementia.
I’ve talked previously
about the diabetes link.
What about dementia?
“Elevated Serum Pesticide Levels
and Risk for Alzheimer Disease.”
A research team at Rutgers found
significantly higher blood
levels of DDE in Alzheimer’s disease
patients compared to controls,
and autopsy studies
show blood levels
are a good proxy for brain levels.
Those with the highest levels
were at about four times
the odds of being
demented with Alzheimer's.
And in a petri dish, DDE increases
amyloid precursor protein levels
in human brain cells, providing
a potential mechanism.
Here are the levels of the
sticky protein implicated in the
development of Alzheimer's
disease before and after some DDE
is added, at the levels one finds
circulating in highly exposed
individuals in the general population.
Put all these studies together,
and there does indeed seem
to be a link, consistent with
data showing about a doubling
of risk for developing dementia among
those acutely pesticide poisoned.
Among U.S. elders, DDT and its
breakdown product DDE are also
associated with increased risk
of cognitive decline in general.
DDT was extensively
used in the United States
from the 1940s through the 1960s.
At its peak, we were churning
out 180 million pounds a year.
And it’s still in our bodies to this day,
contaminating the bloodstreams of
more than 90 percent of Americans,
and DDE, the pesticide
linked to quadrupling the odds
of Alzheimer’s, were at the highest levels.
It’s still in our bodies because
it’s still in the food supply.
In my last video on the topic,
I noted that the levels of
DDT, DDE, and other banned
pesticides and pollutants
were much lower in the breast
milk from a vegetarian mother
compared to breast milk of
her non-vegetarian sister.
And the largest difference
was noted for DDE,
which was four times lower
in the vegetarian sister.
This is what you see across the
board for these kinds of pollutants.
Food samples were collected from
supermarkets across the U.S.
Here’s what they found
for dioxins and PCBs
in beef, chicken, pork,
processed meat, eggs, fish,
all plant-foods put together,
and dairy products.
These toxins build up the food
chain; so, it makes sense that
the most contaminated foods are
meat, fish, and dairy products.
5 to 10 times higher
levels in meat, eggs,
fish, and dairy than what
they found in plant foods.
And unfortunately, cooking doesn’t
destroy pollutants like DDE—
in fact it may make them
even more concentrated.
And this is for a pesticide
that may increase the risk
of Alzheimer’s disease as
much as if you carried
the so-called Alzheimer’s
gene APOE e4.